Inventory of the Powell Family Papers 1775-1927
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Papers of the Powell Family, 1785-1927, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Papers, 1850-1859. (Box 1-2)
    - Papers, 1852., 11 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
      - S[elina] Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "child," [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 27 December 1852., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
        Much family news; sleet and bad weather; religious discussion and viewpoints; Lucy and John[?] have a daughter now.
      - Document signed by Jno. M. Harrison, John A. Carter, and Geo[rge] Ayre involving the dispersal of Cuthbert Powell's estate, including lots in Alexandria by a commission appointed by Circuit Court of Loudoun County, [Virginia], 1852[?]., 4 pages. D. (Box-folder 1:4)
    - Papers, 1853., 19 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
      - Selina Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "dear Father," [John Lloyd], n.p., 19 January 1853., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Mr. Powell, [Charles] and Richard Lloyd] are busy with new business as "Land Agents"; town of Henry, [Illinois] now has a newspaper and a steam mill; hopes to have a railroad passing through soon; there is not a decent Church and she wishes to see one built; Lloyd [Powell], son of Selina, studies German because there are so many Germans in their town to do business with.
      - Minna Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to [Rebecca Powell], 7 February 1853., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Sarcastically teases her sister about differences between lifestyles of "Far West" and the East; Uncle Fred [?] went to Springfield to see that railroad went from Peoria through Henry, [Illinois]; mentions problems with scarlet fever; family news.
      - Jane Janney, Baltimore, [Maryland], to "Becca," [Rebecca Powell], n.p., [28 February] 1853., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Speaks of liquor laws and problems with drinking; describes lectures; such family and town news; mentions other religious lectures.
      - S[elina] P[owell], Henry, [Illinois], to "dear child," [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 1 March 1853., 4 pages. ASL. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Expresses desire for daughter Rebecca to return home; Minna Powell still having problems with headaches; much family news; Fred[?] went to Chicago to see stockholders of the Peoria and Rock Island Railroad; asks for Rebecca to send asparagus seed and large lima beans; mentions Thackery's lectures, and gives her opinion about his books and religious teachings.
      - S[elina] Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "daughter," [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 11 March 1853., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Much family news; "land business" will provide many opportunities for travel; Rebecca planning to go to Leesburg soon.
        Including ANS from C[harles] L. Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "darling," [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 11 March 1853, sending his daughter ten dollars and writing her as to how to handle her expenses and requesting her to bring home her Grandfather's papers. 2 pages.
      - Minna [Powell], Henry [Illinois], to "Brother" [Lloyd Powell], [Lacon, Illinois], 22 March [1853]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        States that even though he just left yesterday, she wanted to put a letter in the books to be sent to him; comments on their inability to see each other even though he is only seven miles away.
      - Lloyd [Powell], Lacon, [Illinois], to Minna E. Powell, Henry, Illinois, 28 March [1853?]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Mentions his job as a traveling salesman and how he hopes to soon be Uncle Richard's [Lloyd] administration; resolved in town meeting to build the Railroad Peoria and Chicago.
      - [Jane Janney], Baltimore, [Maryland], to Re[Becca] [Powell], n.p. 24 [April] [18]53., 2 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Expresses her disappointment that she cannot see Rebecca before Rebecca returns to Henry, Illinois; describes the friendship between them; news of friends in Baltimore.
      - Minna [Powell], Henry, [Illinois], to "Brother," n.p., 29 April 1853., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Tells of carriage accident involving Mr. and Mrs. Richard Dulaney, where their horses were scared by the Clifton Mill and threw Mrs. Dulaney; she and father attended Dr. Rutherford's lectures; emphasizes that ladies got to vote, as well as gentlemen, on whether they were satisfied with the lectures; new wharf boat has arrived.
      - "Brother" Lloyd [Powell], Rushville, [Illinois], to Minna [Powell],[Henry, Illinois], 6 May 1853., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Describes the towns of Rushville and Pittsfield; said he enjoyed Pittfield more, but that Uncle Rich[ar]d [Lloyd] sent him an assignment for Rushville; says he will be there about a month; asks about friends and family.
      - S[elina] Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "son," [Lloyd Powell], n.p., 11 May 1853., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Rebecca has come home; Minna joined the church with her family; gives religious views; family news.
        Including ALS from Minna [Powell], Henry, [Illinois], to "brother," n.p., 11 May 1853, referring to Rushville, as location of brother; tells of beautiful spring weather and describes scenery. 1 page.
      - Minna Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "Brother," 19 May [18]53., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Will soon be coming home; complains of sore throat and headaches; has had scarlet fever; family information.
      - John Smith[?], n.p. to [Jane Janney], n.p., 30 May 1853[?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Tells a story about "Miss Jane" - a mutual friend; says he and Dr. Winslow found her in her parlor with a man; says the servant did not want to let them in and that it was an uncomfortable situation.
        Including ALS written in margins from "Cousin" Jane, n.p. to Re[Becca] [Powell], n.p. concerning religious publication, an Episcopal convention. 4 pages.
      - Minna E. Powell, n.p. to "Brother," [Lloyd Powell], n.p., [June 1853?]., 4 pages. ASL. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Expresses how much she misses him; discusses reading material.
      - Harriet Powell, "Locust Hill", [Loudoun County, Virginia], to "sister," n.p., 30 August 1853., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Describes Aunt Ellen's [Powell Gray] recovery from an illness; much family news; describes wedding that she went to; expresses romantic interest in a Dr. Claggett; includes printed poems.
      - Harriet Powell, "Llangollen," [Virginia], to [Sister], n.p., 4 October 1853., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Describes physical appearance of "Llangollen" as well as her feelings towards the place; reminisces about when family lived in Virginia. And tells about all of old friends; much family news also.
      - Harriet Powell, "Llangollen," [Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 10 October 1853., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Tells her little sister Nina about old friends and family; gives details of things she has been doing.
        Including ALS from "Hatty" [Harriet Powell], "Llangollen," [Virginia], to "Mother," [Selina Powell], n.p., 10 October 1853. Concerning warmer clothes; advantages of "flannel draws" over a "wadded petticoat." 1 page.
      - M. C. Lee, Arlington, [Virginia], to Selina Powell, Louisville, [Kentucky], 10 October [1851-1853]., 3 pages. ALS. Including Xcy. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Says she has been extremely ill and so have many in the area; says she has been traveling in order to improve her health; tells of her problems with Custis and his lessons; says Robert is still holding his office in Washington but wishes to leave; asks how she likes "the West" and if her husband is finding success; news of friends.
      - "Hatty" [Harriet Powell], Alexandria, [Virginia], to "Sister," n.p., 5 November [18]53., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
        Reports Lucy's[?] death and grief everyone feels; Nelly[?] is to be baptized; other family news.
    - Papers, 1854., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
      - Charley [Charles L. Powell, Jr.] [Marshall County?] to "Sister," [Rebecca Powell], [Baltimore, Maryland], [January, ante 1854]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Tells of their Christmas and New Years celebrations.
        Also includes ALS from "mother" S[elina] Powell, to [Re]Bec[ca] [Powell]. Expresses job that Rebecca can be with her relatives in Baltimore; discusses the nature of receiving advice and making her own decisions concerning her travel plans.
      - Harriet Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "sister," n.p., 3 January 1854., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Speaks of attending a party; mentions "matching up" procedures at party; family news; details Christmas gifts.
      - Catharine Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to "son," n.p., 16 January [18]54., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Mentions religious feelings; speaks of a railroad being built nearby; Virginia[?] had her annual get-together on December 26; of family members; mentions a friend's visit to the Crystal Palace[?]; Mrs. Augustine Washington had the first male child born at Mt. Vernon recently; much family news; mentions [Rear Admiral] Leven Minn Powell.
      - "Hatty" [Harriet Powell], Alexandria, [Virginia], to "Sister," [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 9 March 1854., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Mentions Brooks'[?] wedding; describes details of the wedding; much family news.
      - [Jane Janney], Baltimore, [Maryland], to [Re]Becca [Powell], n.p., 14[?] [March] 18[54]., 4 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Tells of her day spent with Lizzie King and Jane Norris; describes a dinner given for a couple about to get married; news of other friends.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to "daughter," [Rebecca Powell], [Henry, Illinois], 30 March 1854., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Mentions sicknesses of Nelson [Lloyd] and John [Lloyd]; speaks of a Douglas Forrest who attends Yale College; has to take a boat to Washington, [D.C.]; gives price rates per acre of land at that time; gives prices for a lot of land.
      - "Mother," [Selina Powell], Alexandria, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell], Henry, Illinois, 12 April 1854., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Much family news about cousins Nannie and Fanny[?]; mentions Uncle Nelson's [Lloyd] recovery; travels by omnibus.
      - Rebecca Powell, Henry, [Illinois], to "father," [Charles L. Powell], Loudoun, [Virginia], 21 April 1854., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Much family news; describes her garden and its contents; Regina[?] was married; Mr. Livingston[?] requests influence of Charles L. Powell to obtain the Consulship of London through General Baercel[?]; mentions Mr. McFaddin as being the mayor of Henry.
      - Charles L. Powell, Locust Hill, [Virginia], to Nina Powell, [Henry, Illinois], 1 May 1854., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Much family news; describes the scenery at Locust Hill; some of Uncle George's[?] children have chicken pox.
      - Description of Minna Powell's death bed by her sister, Rebecca Powell, [May 1854]. (Box-folder 1:6)
        [Identified as much of note added in unknown handwriting, possibly that of Selina Lloyd Hepburn.]
      - Lloyd Powell, [Henry, Illinois], to "Mother" [Selina (Lloyd) Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], [post May 26, 1854]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Description of Minna's gravesite; tells what he's doing to improve its appearance.
      - C[harles] L. Powell[Brother], East Hampton, [New York], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 8 October 1854., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Describes trip to Niagara Falls; describes places visited in New York and where he lives; describes his studies.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, brother, East Hampton, [New York], to "Nean," [Nina Powell], n.p., 14 October [1854]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
        Describes courses he is studying at school; describes the first time he saw a man dive under water and the suit he wore below water; staying at a boarding house.
      - Closing portion of father's sermon given at funeral of John Lloyd, Selina Lloyd Powell's brother, 1854., 4 pages. AMS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      - List of articles for Mrs. Selina Powell left in the estate of her father, [ca. 1854]. (Box-folder 1:6)
        John Lloyd who died in 1854; estimated price value are given.
    - Charles L. Powell, brother, East Hampton, [New York], to Nina [Powell],[Henry, Illinois], [7?] January 1855., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Describes study habits and classes; mentions prices of a ring and a clock; describes his financial situation.
    - [Jane Janney], Baltimore [Maryland], to [Re]Becca [Powell], n.p., 13 [January] [18]55., 4 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Describes in detail her Quaker wedding on December 14, 1854 in which she married Frank[?]; describes the festivities following the wedding.
    - C[harles] L. Powell, brother, East Hampton, [New York], to Nina [Powell], Henry, Illinois, 21 January [1855]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Nina's Christmas gift from Charles arrived safely; mentions wedding of a fellow student; serenaded the couple with a "horse fiddle"; describes his activities in his spelling class; mentions plans to return home in the spring.
    - C[harles] L. Powell, brother, Williston Seminary, East Hampton, [New York], to Nina [Powell],[Henry, Illinois], 8 February [sic] [March] 1855., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Expresses religious beliefs; lists prices for renting his room.
    - C[harles] L. Powell, Hartford [Connecticut], to Nina [Powell],[Henry, Illinois], 3 April 1855., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Describes Charter Oak, an attraction in Hartford; describes his visit to an armory; staying with a Mr. Parsons and describes his family.
    - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Father" [Charles L. Powell], [Alexandria, Virginia], 7 November [18]55., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Discusses financial settlements he is making for his father concerning the house, lands, furniture; says Uncle Fred and Uncle Neb are leaving Henry and they are all "disgusted" with Henry and that he thinks his (father's) decision not to come back was wise; mentions the family move to Winchester, Virginia.
    - Papers, 1856., 12 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "sister" [Rebecca Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 14 January 1856., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Describes their Christmas which was spent at Uncle Fred's and Aunt Lute's; describes a Christmas ball and a New Year's ball in detail; says he has had some problems with dyspepsia; asks about cousin Kate's wedding to a senator.
      - Lloyd Powell, Alton, Illinois, to "Mother," Selina Powell, [Winchester, Virginia], 22 January 1856., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Reports on Aunt Lib and Uncle R[?]'s new son, Richard; says he rented out their house in Henry; says he has been away from "home" now for three months; and will not go to New Orleans, Mobile, and Augusta; describes how he decorated Minna's grave, and expresses hope that her resting place will soon be Virginia; asks about their school; sends money from a large profit he made selling land.
      - Lloyd Powell, Cairo, Illinois, to "sister" [Rebecca Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 25 February 1856. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Describes his visit to Louisville where he visited cousins and went to many social events; says that the train ride from Kentucky was very rough traveling; says he will be in Vicksburg in a week and then will go to Wilmington, North Carolina; Mobile, Alabama; New Orleans; and Memphis, Tennessee; asks about family and friends.
      - Lloyd Powell, Lake Ponchartrain Steamer California [en route to Mobile, Alabama], to Hatty [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 12 March 1856. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Describes his stay in Vicksburg, and his visit with Mr. And Mrs. Eilbeck Mason and Miss Louisa Fox; says that he did not see Cousin John Russell while in New Orleans; discusses his travel plans; asks about Hatty's teaching.
      - Lloyd Powell, New Orleans, [Louisiana], to "sister," [Rebecca Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 14 April 1856., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Expresses joy that she is well from the influenza; says he has recently traveled to Portsmouth, Virginia, the Carolinas, Georgia, Alabama and Mississippi; says he will now go to Texas; discusses travel plans; asks her to pick out one of her friends for him; discusses Charlie's new job in St. Louis.
      - "Charley" [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], Saint Louis, [Missouri], to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 4 May [18]56., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Describes St. Louis and the Virginia House Hotel; inquires about the new scholars the family has taken on; harasses Nina for not writing.
        Including ANS from C[harles] L. Powell, Saint Louis, [Missouri], to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 4 May [18]56 concerning his happiness about Nina joining the Church. 1 page.
      - Frank [George Francis Lloyd], Henry, Illinois, to [?], 9 May 1856., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Describes hard times in Illinois; intent to move back to Virginia when business picks up; family news.
      - Catharine Powell, Bellvue [sic], [Alexandria?], [Virginia], to "granddaughter," [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 15 May [18]56., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Speaks of influenza and other illnesses prominent in the town; reports the death of Mr. Adies [?]; Ellen [Powell] is in Washington Infirmary; house is being renovated; family news.
      - Lloyd Powell, St. Louis, [Missouri], to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia]. 7 June 1856., 4 pages. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Says he just returned from Henry; says Charlie is on his way to Henry to start his new job in Uncle Fred's store; describes Henry and the house they used to live in; reports that Uncle Fred is building a house; gives new of Scholastics and Monsieur Carlo; says he will go to Pennsylvania next and then visit them.
      - "Charles" [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], Henry, [Illinois], to Nina [Powell], Winchester, Virginia, 20 July 1856., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Reports that Lloyd [Powell] is on his way to Virginia; describes their yard and home in Henry; yellow fever is not a problem this year in Illinois; he went to a concert given by the Baleis.
      - Llolyd Powell, Pittsburg, Pennsylvania to "Sister" [Hattie Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 9 November [18]56., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Inquires about the "weddings fair"; discusses his travels and the loneliness involved in his job; mentions his relief that the campaigns and elections are over; sends messages to friends at home.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, [Illinois], to Nina [Powell], Winchester, Virginia, 17 November 1856., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Nina has begun studying Latin and learning how to draw; mentions the extension of the Chicago and Pern canal down to Henry; much family news.
    - Papers, 1857., 16 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
      - "Mother" [Selina Powell], Winchester, [Virginia], to Charlie [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry, Illinois], 15 February [1857]., 6 pages. AL. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Tells what each family member is doing; discusses religion and the duties of a Christian; gives news of friends who have joined the church; discusses Minna's grave; discusses letter writing; tells of recent marriages and engagements; gives her philosophy on why he should not begin to chew tobacco; news of family and friends.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, Jr., Henry, Illinois, to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 22 February 1857., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Makes reference to Valentine's Day and Washington's Birthday; mentions last year's parade and the marching continentals; reports of bad rain storm that tore up the railroad track and caused problems with mud and flooding; much family news.
        Including ANS from C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 22 February 1857, telling her to turn to their one friend for strength and advice [God?]. 1 page.
      - Lloyd Powell, Saint Louis, Missouri, to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 22 February [18]57., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Describes a storm which kept him in Henry, Illinois, unable to travel; gives recent travel plans, including a trip to Philadelphia by boat; gives news of friends and family in Henry; says many river towns are flooded.
      - Lloyd Powell, Charleston, South Carolina, to "Mother" [Selina Lloyd Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 12 April [18]57., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Gives news of relatives in Alexandria; tells his travel plans; says he finds the women of Virginia far more appealing than those of South Carolina.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, Illinois, to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], 14 June [18]57., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Uncle Fred[?] and Aunt Lucy[?] are leaving for Virginia; sending his mother his daguerreotype, a photograph; reports that Lloyd is in St. Louis; Bridget, a past boarder, had a little girl; much family news.
      - S[elina] Powell, Capon Springs, [West Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Winchester, Virginia], [August 1857]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Describes the family vacation and adventures; describes the baths; mentions the parties they have attended; family news.
      - S[elina] Powell, Capen [sic] Springs [Capon Springs], [West Virginia], to "Charley" [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry, Illinois], 7 August 1857., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Family is on vacation; describes activities and scenery at Capon Springs; much family news.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, [Jr.], Henry, [Illinois], to Nina Powell, Winchester, Virginia, 9 August [18]57., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Speaks about taking inventory at the store; much family news.
      - Selina Powell, Winchester, [Virginia] to Nina [Powell], 22 August [1857?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Says they just got back from Capon; asks her not to take nitrate of silver for her headaches; says they have all improved their health by the visit to Capon; says "brother" Nelson is now there hoping the springs will help him; says they did not get the house that they wanted to rent; gives news of friends; says Rebecca, Hatty, and Lloyd are there.
        Including ALS from C[harles L.] Powell to Nina [Powell]. Says that he misses her and wishes she could have been at Capon; asks about her headaches.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Mother" [Selina Lloyd Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 12 October [18]57., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Describes his travels from Baltimore to Henry; mentions shortage of money due to bank failures; gives detailed news of the town, including improvements being made; news of Henry relatives; mentions that the bank failures will result in fewer land dealings and therefore, less work for him; asks about the young ladies of Winchester.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, Jr., Henry, Illinois, to Nina Powell, Winchester, Virginia, 15 November [1857?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Inquires about Mr. Waler's[?] lectures; now attends the Methodist Church; reports of the adventures during hunting season; mentions the new idea of pavement sidewalks.
      - Lloyd Powell, Henry, Illinois, to "Sister" [Hattie Powell], [Winchester, Virginia], 1 December 1857., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Describes a severe snowstorm and its effects on Henry; tells how he spent Thanksgiving day; describes their new cook with whom he is infatuated; mentions the death of Robert Conrad[?]; gives messages of friends in Winchester.
      - S[elina] Powell, Winchester, [Virginia], to "Charlie," [Charles L. Powell, Jr.], [Henry, Illinois], 9 December 1857., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:1)